<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Project Blog (Posts about douglas hofstadter)</title><link>https://victor-shepardson.github.io/blog/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://victor-shepardson.github.io/blog/categories/douglas-hofstadter.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 16 Apr 2018 18:41:39 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Bear Cult and HOFSTADTERPILLAR</title><link>https://victor-shepardson.github.io/blog/posts/bear-cult-and-hofstadterpillar/</link><dc:creator>Victor Shepardson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;These are two animations I made for FS35 with Jodie Mack in winter 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Bear Cult&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bear Cult&lt;/em&gt; was inspired by a collection of Joseph Campbell's essays I found in a used book store. I was struck by a chapter entitled "Renewal Myths and Rites of the Primitive Hunters and Planters". (It was written in 1960 so I don't know how current the ideas are). It's about the prehistoric (even pre-human) origins of myth. In Campbell's telling, the purpose of myth is to conquer death. Campbell claims that preserved arrangements of cave bear bones are evidence for the ancient roots of a bear-baiting ritual still practiced by indigenous peoples in northern Japan. In the bear-baiting ritual, a young bear is captured, raised in captivity, and then ritually tortured, killed and eaten. The bear is believed to contain the soul of a demigod which yearns to be released from its fleshy bear-prison. For Campbell, this is the coping mechanism of an animal who kills to survive but understands death. It's the hunter's moral justification for killing: death isn't real, killing is a kindness. Ritualized death is a point of contact with the &lt;em&gt;numinous&lt;/em&gt;: a sense of awe at contemplation of the infinite at the root of the religious and scientific impulses. I found the deep connection Campbell makes between this most sacred feeling and man's capacity for cruelty heartbreaking. (side note: &lt;em&gt;awe&lt;/em&gt; smells to me an awful lot like the notion of &lt;em&gt;intrinsic motivation&lt;/em&gt; in reinforcement learning: a positive feeling obtained by beholding and questioning the world; and the numinous smells like an overwhelming double-dose of awe)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I set out to depict a bear-baiting ritual. Not the real, specific practice Campbell describes, but the abstracted elements of a hypothetical prehistoric bear cult. The body of the bear would be made with paper drawings and cutouts, while the soul would be made with &lt;a href="https://victor-shepardson.github.io/blog/posts/video-feedback"&gt;virtual video feedback&lt;/a&gt;. These material and digital components would interact via fluorescent orange paper which would be keyed out in software. An good alternate tile might be "Mind-Body Chromakey". Originally I storyboarded a longer story including human hands and spears piercing the bear and the escape of its soul. Only the first "enter the bear" bit proved feasible for a midterm project. I'm very happy with how the bear soul material turned out. I exported the key as a binary mask and incorporated it in the feedback process, so the roiling cloud-forms conform to the geometry of the bear eyes and nose-hole. On the other hand the black-on-black paper was a terrible idea. I really needed black felt or something for the background. This project also taught me how sound influences the perception of time in film: what felt like a good visual rhythm when I was silently animating seems weirdly abbreviated with the soundtrack added. The sound was a bit rushed, but I like the general effect. It's some recordings of bear vocalizations and some carcass-mangling sounds chopped up into phase-rhythms using Max. I would love to revisit this project some day with lessons learned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="video-wrapper"&gt;
  &lt;div class="video"&gt;
    &lt;iframe src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/199104868" width="100%" height="100%" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;HOFSTADTERPILLAR&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This one was my final project for the course. To be continued...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="video-wrapper"&gt;
  &lt;div class="video"&gt;
    &lt;iframe src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/121756116" width="100%" height="100%" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>aftereffects</category><category>animation</category><category>bear cult</category><category>douglas hofstadter</category><category>feedback</category><category>hofstadterpillar</category><category>jodie mack</category><category>joseph campbell</category><category>max</category><category>sonic</category><category>visual</category><guid>https://victor-shepardson.github.io/blog/posts/bear-cult-and-hofstadterpillar/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 12 Jan 2017 03:46:32 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Video Feedback</title><link>https://victor-shepardson.github.io/blog/posts/video-feedback/</link><dc:creator>Victor Shepardson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Way back in high school I read Douglas Hofstadter's &lt;a href="https://archive.org/details/GEBen_201404"&gt;Gödel, Escher, Bach&lt;/a&gt;. There are about a hundred captivating ideas in there, and just one of them is the concept of video feedback: connect a video camera to a screen, and then point it at the screen. Weird stuff happens on the screen. Around the same time I was discovering that the audio feedback of wiggling an electric around in front of an amp is more fun than drilling scales.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an undergrad, I became interested in computer graphics. I was especially taken with the idea of &lt;em&gt;procedural graphics&lt;/em&gt;: generating images from nothing but math, as opposed to using assets made by virtually drawing (as in photoshop) or digitizing reality (as with a digital camera). Procedural graphics can translate some of the tantalizing infinites of mathematics into rich sensory experiences! In particular &lt;a href="http://www.iquilezles.org/www/articles/warp/warp.htm"&gt;this brief article&lt;/a&gt; by Íñigo Quílez had me enthralled by the idea of turning a random number generator into an endless alien terrain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eventually I put two and two together: you can dispense with the video camera and program a completely virtual video feedback process. And once you do, it can do much weirder things than a video camera. This was hardly unknown in computer graphics, yet was weirdly unpopular. There's a preoccupation with statelessness in the scene Quílez is part of; &lt;a href="https://www.shadertoy.com/"&gt;Shadertoy&lt;/a&gt; didn't render to texture until 2016! Academic CG tends to focus on predictability and utility for efficient, photorealistic rendering; feedback is unruly and difficult to analyze. Then there are fractals, which are iterated, but not open ended: you iterate to convergence, rather than letting the image evolve as in video feedback. However &lt;a href="http://csc.ucdavis.edu/~chaos/"&gt;Jim Crutchfield&lt;/a&gt; has written about the dynamics of digital video feedback from a math/physics perspective. 2-D cellular automata like Conway's game of life can be thought of as digital video feedback, and there's a whole &lt;a href="http://golly.sourceforge.net/"&gt;hobbyist community&lt;/a&gt; there, not to mention the &lt;a href="http://alife.org/"&gt;academic artificial life community&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="http://www.wolframscience.com/"&gt;Stephen Wolfram&lt;/a&gt;'s insular "new kind of science". The whole field of computational fluid dynamics is doing a similar thing with a different set of priorities! And of course video feedback shows up in fine art beginning (?) with video artists like Nam June Paik.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally in the fall of 2014 after encountering such cool dudes as &lt;a href="http://sabrinaratte.com/"&gt;Sabrina Ratté&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://www.alexanderdupuis.com/"&gt;Alex Dupuis&lt;/a&gt; I was galvanized to get some feedback of my own going. Still blissfully ignorant of much, I started making stuff like this (more recent) doodle:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="100%" height="332" frameborder="0" src="https://www.shadertoy.com/embed/MdcSW8?gui=true&amp;amp;t=10&amp;amp;paused=true&amp;amp;muted=false" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Incidentally &lt;a href="https://synesthesia.live/"&gt;these folks&lt;/a&gt; licensed the above shader to use in their music-reactive visuals software Synesthesia. It looks pretty neat, though I haven't been able to mess with it myself since I don't have a Mac. Maybe take a look if you do.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eventually this would grow into such projects as &lt;a href="https://victor-shepardson.github.io/blog/posts/abstract-concrete/"&gt;ABSTRACT/CONCRETE&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://victor-shepardson.github.io/blog/posts/convnet-video-feedback/"&gt;Video Synthesis With Convolutional Autoencoders&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://victor-shepardson.github.io/blog/posts/cortical-sonification"&gt;Data Sonification Using a Cortical Representation of Sound&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>douglas hofstadter</category><category>feedback</category><category>shadertoy</category><category>visual</category><guid>https://victor-shepardson.github.io/blog/posts/video-feedback/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 12 Jan 2017 03:08:22 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>