<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Project Blog (Posts about max)</title><link>https://victor-shepardson.github.io/blog/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://victor-shepardson.github.io/blog/categories/max.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 16 Apr 2018 20:35:04 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Bear Cult and HOFSTADTERPILLAR</title><link>https://victor-shepardson.github.io/blog/posts/bear-cult-and-hofstadterpillar/</link><dc:creator>Victor Shepardson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;These are two animations I made for FS35 with Jodie Mack in winter 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Bear Cult&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bear Cult&lt;/em&gt; was inspired by a collection of Joseph Campbell's essays I found in a used book store, specifically one entitled "Renewal Myths and Rites of the Primitive Hunters and Planters". It's about the prehistoric origins of myth. In Campbell's telling, the purpose of myth is to conquer death. Campbell cites preserved arrangements of cave bear bones as evidence for the ancient roots of a bear-baiting ritual still practiced by indigenous peoples in northern Japan. In the bear-baiting ritual, a young bear is captured, raised in captivity, and then ritually tormented, killed and eaten. The bear is believed to contain the soul of a demigod which yearns to be released from its fleshy bear-prison. For Campbell, this is the coping mechanism of an animal which kills to survive but understands death. It's the hunter's moral justification for killing: death isn't terminal, killing is a kindness. Ritualized death is a point of contact with the numinous; the fear of death is transmuted to awe. I found the deep connection Campbell makes between this sacred feeling and human capacity for cruelty heartbreaking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I decided to depict a bear-baiting ritual. Not the specific cultural practice Campbell recounts, but the abstracted elements of a hypothetical prehistoric bear cult. The body of the bear would be made by hand with paper drawings and cutouts, while the soul would be made in software with &lt;a href="https://victor-shepardson.github.io/blog/posts/video-feedback"&gt;virtual video feedback&lt;/a&gt;. These material and digital components would interact via fluorescent orange paper which could be keyed out in video editing software. A possible alternate title: "Mind-Body Chromakey". Originally I had storyboarded a longer narrative including human hands and spears piercing the bear and the escape of its soul, but only part proved feasible in the time I had.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm happy with how the bear soul material turned out. After shooting the paper animation, I exported just the key as a binary mask. As an input to the feedback process, the mask lets the roiling cloud-forms conform to the geometry of the bear eyes and nose-hole. Unfortunately the black-on-black paper was unwise; there's a lot of camera noise after adjusting the levels to make everything visible. A darker background of black felt or something might have worked better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project taught a lesson about how sound influences the perception of time in film. What felt like a good visual rhythm when I was silently animating seems weirdly abbreviated with the soundtrack added. The sound was a bit rushed, but I like the general effect. It's some recordings of bear vocalizations and carcass-mangling sounds chopped up into phase-rhythms with the same methods I used for &lt;a href="https://victor-shepardson.github.io/blog/posts/siba"&gt;SIBA&lt;/a&gt;. I'd like to revisit this project someday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="video-wrapper"&gt;
  &lt;div class="video"&gt;
    &lt;iframe src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/199104868" width="100%" height="100%" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;HOFSTADTERPILLAR&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This one was my final project for the course. To be continued...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="video-wrapper"&gt;
  &lt;div class="video"&gt;
    &lt;iframe src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/121756116" width="100%" height="100%" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>aftereffects</category><category>animation</category><category>bear cult</category><category>douglas hofstadter</category><category>feedback</category><category>hofstadterpillar</category><category>jodie mack</category><category>joseph campbell</category><category>max</category><category>sonic</category><category>visual</category><guid>https://victor-shepardson.github.io/blog/posts/bear-cult-and-hofstadterpillar/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 12 Jan 2017 03:46:32 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Bendy: Wavetable Automata in Max</title><link>https://victor-shepardson.github.io/blog/posts/bendy/</link><dc:creator>Victor Shepardson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;In spring of 2015 I made a synthesizer called Bendy as a seminar project. A technical description and a Max/MSP implementation can be found on &lt;a href="https://github.com/victor-shepardson/bendy"&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;. Here's what is sounds like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="100%" height="166" scrolling="no" frameborder="no" src="https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/209732439&amp;amp;color=ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>feedback</category><category>generative</category><category>max</category><category>sonic</category><guid>https://victor-shepardson.github.io/blog/posts/bendy/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 09 Jan 2017 23:26:25 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>SIBA I|II|III</title><link>https://victor-shepardson.github.io/blog/posts/SIBA/</link><dc:creator>Victor Shepardson</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;In 2014 I spent a lot of time working through a Steve Reich obsession by making tape music. This piece was eventually presented at ICMC 2015. SIBA I|II|III stands for "Studies In Being Alive One Two and Three", which was a joke about the lack of purpose I felt at the time and also a genuine attempt to describe what I was groping toward, stylized to reflect the asemic repetitious sound-destruction therein. I don't know how to feel about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="500" height="600" scrolling="no" frameborder="no" allow="autoplay" src="https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/playlists/97523789&amp;amp;color=%2399aadd&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=true&amp;amp;show_comments=false&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;show_teaser=true&amp;amp;visual=true"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>max</category><category>phasing</category><category>sonic</category><category>steve reich</category><category>tape music</category><guid>https://victor-shepardson.github.io/blog/posts/SIBA/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 09 Jan 2017 23:26:25 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>